U-M-D Lamb Watch, where normal is a lamb in a bucket.
But let's start at the beginning.
Animal Science 245, Sheep Management,
a.k.a. Lamb Watch, transforms students into shepherds.
There's class, jugs, mucking the stalls, chalkboards, whiteboard, paperwork, heat lamps,
grain, hay, lots of hay, cows, horses, cats, and of course,
sheep.
13 U's deliver between 13 to 26 lambs during the course.
List has two lambs.
And give novice student shepherds a chance to apply their in-class lessons.
We help out with the first physical exams, looking at the respiratory rates,
the temperature of the U's and the lambs,
and the weight of the lambs.
Farm work is a 24-7 operation.
Rain, shine, or snow. And there is always something to do.
A few chores that we do have while working on the farm,
run into the water and take cleaning, sweeping, feeding,
and you have to be on top of everything.
Especially when watching over pregnant animals.
Yes, are you happy?
Yes, my love, yes.
The sheep, they're very friendly and it's so fun to be around sheep.
Are you hungry?
After birth, a leg bath, and bonding time with the U,
lambs need a thorough checkup from the student shepherds
to keep the flock healthy and happy.
Shepherds keep out infection by dunking umbilical cords
and hooves in iodine, and weigh the lambs
to ensure they are getting proper nutrition.
As more lambs join the herd, the farm pace speeds up.
Rub notes wait, feed clean hay, rub notes wait,
feed clean hay, rub notes wait.
Until all of the lambs are born,
and a flock of 13 at the beginning of February
has expanded to 39.
Landwatch and taking care of pregnant sheep
has been really fun and rewarding.
Being able to be a part of a birth and help out if needed,
even though we're students, I really do appreciate that.
So the most meaningful part about being in this sheep management class
is this is just not a quiz or an assignment.
These are lives that we're taking care of.
And that's very meaningful to me
because I get to see them grow up and develop
based on how much I take care of them,
how much I know of them from lectures.
The student shepherds will continue
with their farm responsibilities.
In the meantime, shhhhhh,
let's give the U's and lambs some time to rest.
Thank you.